A Guide to the F. Peyton Rous papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA194
Rockefeller Archive Center
F. Peyton Rous papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rous, Peyton
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA194
1 Cubic Feet
1 box and 7 bound volumes.
Biographical/Historical note
(Francis) Peyton Rous, (1879-1970) pathologist and bacteriologist at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1909 until his death in 1970 who made outstanding contributions on cancer and virus research and worked also in liver physiology and pathology and vascular physiology. Winner of the Nobel Prize in Medicine in 1966.
Biographical note
1879 Born October 5, Baltimore, Maryland
1900 B.A. Johns Hopkins University
1905 M.D. Johns Hopkins Medical School
1905-1906 Resident House Officer, Johns Hopkins Hospital
1906-1908 Instructor in Pathology, University of Michigan
1909-1910 Assistant in Pathology and Bacteriology, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York
1910-1912 Associate, RIMR
1912-1920 Associate Member, RIMR
1920-1945 Member, RIMR
1945- Member Emeritus, RIMR
1970 Died February 16, New York City
1918-1922 National Research Council (Vice Chairman, Med. Div. 1918)
1923-1926 National Research Council
1929 Linacre Lecturer, Cambridge University
1929 Honorary Fellow, Trinity Hall
1957-1970 Board of Scientific Consultants, Sloan-Kettering Institute; Board of Scientific Advisers, Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund; Co-editor, Journal of Experimental Medicine
Honorary Degrees
1938 Sc. D. Cambridge University
1938 Sc. D. University of Michigan
1949 Sc. D. Yale University
1949 Sc. D. University of Birmingham
1949 Sc. D. McGill University
1954 Sc. D. University of Chicago
1959 Sc. D. Rockefeller University
1966 Sc. D. Jefferson University
1967 Sc. D. University of Hartford
Honorary M.D.
1946 M.D. University of Zurich
1966 M D. Jefferson Medical College
1963 LL. D. (Honorary) St. Lawrence University
Awards
1927 John Scott Medal and Award
1941 Walker Prize, Royal College of Surgeons, London
1952 Anna Fuller Award
1953 Kober Medal, Association of American Physicians
1954 Bertner Medal and Award, University of Texas
1956 Kovalenko Medal, National Academy of Sciences
1957 Distinguished Service Award, American Cancer Society
1958 Lasker Award, American Public health Association
1958 Landsteiner Award, American Association of Blood Banks
1959 New York Academy of Medicine Medal
1959 Judd Award, Memorial Center for Cancer
1962- Gold Medal, Royal Society of Medicine (London)
1962 United Nations Prize for Cancer Research
1964 Gold Headed Cane award, Am. Assoc. of Pathologists and Bacteriologists
1966 Cleveland Medal, American Cancer Society
1966 National Medal of Science
1966 Paul Ehrlich Award, Germany
1966 Nobel Prize in Medicine
Member of: American Association for the Advancement of Science, Fellow, National Academy of Sciences, American Philosophical Society, Association of American Physicians, American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists, American Society for Experimental Pathology, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, Harvey Society, New York Pathological Society, New York Academy of Medicine, American Association for Cancer Research, Phi Beta Kappa, Alpha Omega Alpha, Sigma Xi, Royal Society, Foreign Member, Royal Society Medicine and College of Pathologists, London. Honorary Fellow, Weizmann Institute of Science, Israel. Honorary Fellow, British Physiological Society (Honorary Member), Pathological Society of Great Britain and Ireland (Honorary Member), American Society for Microbiology, New York Pathological Society, Connecticut Medical Society, British Medical Association (foreign Correspondent member), Académie de Médecine, Paris (foreign correspondent member), Royal Academy of Sciences, Denmark, Norwegian Academy of Sciences and Letters, Century Club
Scope and Contents note
Biographical material, newspaper items, photographs, collected papers.
The collection consists primarily of photographs, articles about Peyton Rous on the receipt of various awards, bibliography and collected reprints.
Related Materials
The main body of Peyton Rous papers was deposited at The American Philosophical Society.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 R762
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Biochemistry; Liver -- Physiology; Liver -- Pathology; Biology -- Research; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Bacteriology; Viruses -- Research; Cancer; Pathology; Physiology; Cancer -- Research; Medicine, Preventive; Life sciences; Medical research; Medical sciences; Diseases; Bacteria; Rockefeller University; Rous, Peyton; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Photocopy of Biographical memoir from American Philosophical Society Yearbook, 1971 written by James Stuart Henderson. Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photocopies of Peace Resolution correspondence from Science, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Memoir of Peyton Rous written by Renato Dulbecco with covering correspondence with Dr. Edelman (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Copies of Reports to Corporation and Descriptive Pamphlet, 1941 1941-1942 1942-1944 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical memoir NAS v. 48 (1976) by Renato Dulbecco (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Copy of Presentation Address, Kober Medal, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- News release, Kovalenko Medal, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Time clipping, Lasker Award, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Today's Health, clipping, Lasker Medal, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bull. NY Acad. Med. Academy Medal, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 80th Birthday celebration, 1960 February (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Medical World News, 1960 August (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lab World, Gold Headed Cane, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Nobel Prize articles, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Steven. Pelech, "Cellular Security: How Anti-Cancer Genes Turn Off Tumors" The Sciences, 1989 January-February; pp. 38-44, photocopy (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Official photograph of portrait (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  (Not for distribution except through office of RU Vice-President).
- American Philosophical Society Inventory of Rous Papers (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings, 1929, 1966
  - The Modern Dance of Death, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The Lamentable Decline in Self-Satisfaction", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Publications, separately bound
  - Reprint from Les Prix Nobel en 1966 (Box 1)
  - The Modern Dance of Death by Peyton Rous Linacre Lecture, 1929 Cambridge UP (Box 1)
  - The Dualism of the Discoverer by Peyton Rous Sonderdruck. Die Johann Wolfgang Goethe Universität, 1966 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    This address was made on the occasion of the Paul Ehrlich Award, but it was published without an opportunity for Peyton Rous to check proofs and he therefore did not wish it listed in his bibliography and wanted all copies to be destroyed.
- "Collected Reprints", 6 bound volumes
- Gustav Stern Symposium On Perspectives in virology, v. 2, 1961. In honor of Peyton Rous, 1 bound volume